<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation allowing a further dyet to the Commons for taking the Test, and indemnifying the heretors guilty of harbouring, or resetting of rebels who have taken the Test at the late Justice-Aires, as to their lives</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58709</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1623</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6808</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13708394</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13708394</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101503</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58709)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101503)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 848:44)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation allowing a further dyet to the Commons for taking the Test, and indemnifying the heretors guilty of harbouring, or resetting of rebels who have taken the Test at the late Justice-Aires, as to their lives</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the heir of Andrew Anderson, printer to His Most Sacred Majesty ;</publisher>
                  <publisher>by George Croom ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <pubPlace>Re-printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Given under our signet at Haly-Rud-House, the twentieth of September, One Thousand Six Hundred Eighty and Three ..."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Proclamations --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Oaths --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  Scotland --  Edinburgh (Lothian) --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:101503:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>C<hi rend="sup">2</hi> R</head>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>A PROCLAMATION, Allowing a further Dyet to the Commons for taking the <hi>Teſt,</hi> and Indemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the Heretors Guilty of Harbouring, or Reſetting of Rebels who have taken the <hi>Teſt</hi> at the late Juſtice-Aires, as to their Lives.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>CHARLES R. <lb/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>y the grace of GOD, King of <hi>Great-Britain, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith;</signed>
               <salute>To Our Lyon King at Arms, and his Brethren Heraulds, Macers, Purſevants or Meſſengers at Arms, Our Sheriffs in that part, conjunctly and ſeverally, ſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute Greeting:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>foraſmuch as it being repreſented to Vs, that ſome of Our Commons have, through ignorance, or want of frequent Meetings of theſe appointed by Our late Proclamation for Adminiſtrating the <hi>Teſt,</hi> loſt the benefit of Our Indemnity, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the time formerly allowed unto them was very ſhort, We have thought fit, as a further evidence of Our Clemency, with advice of Our Privy Council, to continue the Dyet for their taking the <hi>Teſt,</hi> to the firſt of <hi>March</hi> next enſuing, for Indemnifying them for ever, as to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetting, and Intercomuning with ſuch as were engaged in the Rebellion, in the year 1679. Excepting ſuch as have Reffetted, or Intercomuned with the Aſſaſſines of the late Lord Arch-biſhop of <hi>St. Andrews,</hi> or Seditious Field-preachers: As alſo, ſuch as have Reſſetted, or Intercomuned with any who is Guilty of, or any maner of way acceſſory to the late horrid Conſpiracy againſt Our Royal Perſon and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Requiring hereby all Sheriffs, Stewarts, Magiſtrates and others in Office ſtrictly to ſearch for, (after the ſaid day,) and to puniſh with all rigor that Our Law will allow, all ſuch as will refuſe this laſt Offer of Our Mercy: But if any are, or ſhall be apprehended before their making application for obtaining this Our Favour, We Declare that they ſhall have no benefit thereof. And further, We de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that the Heretors who have already taken the <hi>Teſt</hi> in the laſt Iuſtice-Aires, thereby are ſecured as to their Lives, if they have been only Guilty of Reſetting, and Intercomuning; but that nevertheleſs, they ſhall after the firſt day of <hi>November</hi> next be lyable to be Conveened before Our Privy Council, and to ſuch Arbitrary Puniſhments as they ſhall think fit to appoint, according to the Specialities of their reſpective Caſes and Guilt; Declaring hereby, that their Sentences being fulfilled by them, ſhall Indemnifie them as effectually, as if they had a ſpecial Pardon and Remiſſion from Vs, under Our great Seal; and We do allow thoſe intruſted by Our Privy Council, to take the Declarations of Witneſſes againſt thoſe who have been ſuſpected of being in the late Rebellion, or Guilty of Reſſetting and Intercomuning, providing always that there be no Proceſſes intented upon theſe; or any other Declarations, or Depoſitions, until Our Advocat ſhall find ſufficient matter of Dittay therein. And to the effect Our Pleaſure may be known in the Premiſſes, Our Will is, and We Charge you ſtraitly and Command, that incontinent, theſe Our Letters ſeen, ye paſs to the Mercat Croſs of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and other places needful, and thereat, in Our Name and Authority, by open Proclamation, make publication of the Premiſſes: The which to do, We commit to you, conjunctly and ſeverally, Our full Power, by theſe Our Letters, delivering them by you duly execute, and indorſed again to the Bearer.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given under Our Signet at <hi>Haly rud-houſe,</hi> 
                  <date>the twenty day of <hi>September,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred eighty and three. And of Our Reign, the thirtieth and fifth Year.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>Per actum Dominorum Secreti Concilij.
<hi>WILL. PATERSON.</hi> Cls. Sti. Concilij</signed>
               <lb/>
GOD ſave the KING.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by the Heir of <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Printer to his moſt Sacred Majeſty, 1683. Re-printed at <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>George Croom,</hi> in <hi>Thames-ſtreet,</hi> over againſt <hi>Baynard</hi>'s <hi>Caſtle,</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
